PIXAR IN A BOX 艾墨镇 aimozhen.com/pixarinabox
PIXAR IN A BOX 艾墨镇 aimozhen.com/pixarinabox
- Now that we can retrace in 2D,
- 现在我们会 2D 中做光线追踪了
we can finally go back to the problem
我们终于可以回到那个
we really wanna solve: retracing in 3D.
我们实际想解决的问题：在 3D 中做光线追踪
In particular, we'll need to retrace flat planes,
具体来说 我们需要光线追踪平面
houses, and, ultimately, characters.
房屋和终极目标 角色
A character like Carl is a complex shape
像卡尔这样的角色是很复杂的
but, as we discussed in the character modeling lesson,
但是 正如我们在角色建模课程中讨论的一样
he can be broken down into lots of small,
他能被分解成许多微小的
four-sided quadrilaterals, that is, four-sided polygons.
四边形 也就是 四边面
And each quadrilateral can be converted into two triangles
而每个四边形都可以被转化为两个三角形
by adding an edge that connects diagonal points.
只要加上一条连接对角点的边就可以
That leads to the question:
That leads to the question: 这就引出了一个问题：
How do you intersect a ray with a triangle?
你如何将一条射线和一个三角形相交的呢？
It turns out, that that's one of the most fundamental
这就是光线追踪渲染器
calculations that a ray tracer performs.
需要处理的最基础的运算之一
Here's a scene consisting of just one triangle.
这里就有一个仅有一个三角形的场景
Our real scenes contain millions of triangles.
我们的真实场景含有数百万的三角形
But, once we know how to intersect a single triangle,
但是 一旦我们知道了如何与一个三角形做相交
our ray tracer just keeps doing that, over and over again.
我们的光线追踪渲染器就会一遍又一遍地一直这样做
Now, I don't know about you, but I don't wanna do
嗯 我并不认识你 我也不想
the same thing over and over again.
一遍一遍地重复做一件事情
So, it's a good thing we have computers to help us out
所以 有电脑帮我们做这种事情真是太好了
and that they don't get tired.
它们也不会厌倦这样做的
As in 2D, we start by setting up a coordinate system.
在 2D 中 我们开始于建立起一套坐标系
But, this time, there are three directions: X, Y, and Z.
这次呢 我们有了三个轴向 X、Y 和 Z
As we explained earlier, we pick a camera position,
如同我们早先解释的 我们选一个相机位点
call it C, and a viewing direction.
称为 C 以及一个视向
And we construct an image plane
接着我们构建了一个像平面
perpendicular to the viewing direction.
它与视向垂直
This is where our image will be formed.
我们的图像就在此处产生
Let's pick a pixel, P, on the image plane
让我们选个像平面上的像素点 P
and construct the parametric representation
并建立起射线 CP 的参数方程
of the ray, CP, as R(t) = (1-t)C + tP.
也就是 R(t) = (1-t)*C +t*P
This is the same equation we saw in 2D,
这和我们在 2D 中看到的方程是一样的
but now it represents three separate equations.
但它现在代表了三个分立的方程
One for X coordinates, one for Y coordinates,
一个与 X 坐标相关 一个与 Y 坐标相关
and one for Z coordinates.
一个与 Z 坐标相关
Remember that, in the previous video,
还记得 上个视频中
we saw that, in two dimensions, every line
我们明白 在二维中 每条线
can be written in implicit form as ax + by + c = 0.
都可以写成行隐式 ax+by+c = 0
Very similar to this is the equation for a plane.
与这类似的是一个平面的表达式
And every triangle lies in a plane.
而每个三角形都会落在一个平面内
The equation for a plane can be written in implicit form
平面的隐式方程为
as ax + by + cz + d = 0.
ax+by+cz+d = 0
The intersection point, I, we're looking for,
我们要找的 焦点 I
is in the plane of the triangle,
就在三角形所在的平面上
meaning that aIx + bIy + cIz + d = 0,
也就是 a*I_x+b*I_y+c*I_z+d = 0
where Ix, Iy, and Iz are the coordinates of I.
I_x、I_y 和 I_z 表示 I 的坐标
I is also on the ray, meaning that there's a value of t,
它也同样在射线上 意味着会有一个 t 值
again, let's call it t*, such that I = R(t*)
我们称它为 t* 使得 I = R(t*)
which equals (1-t*)c + t*P
等于 (1-t*)*C + (t*)*P
which is really the three equations shown here.
也就是现在展示的三个方程
One for X, one for Y, and one for Z.
一个表示 X 一个表示 Y 一个表示 Z
Now we have four equations and four unknowns.
现在我们就有了四个方程和四个未知数
To solve this system of equations,
为了解决这个方程组
we can follow the recipe from 2D
我们可以按照 2D 中的方式
and substitute the last three equations into the first one.
将后三个方程带入第一个中
This gives us one equation with only one unknown, t*.
我们就获得了仅有未知数 t* 的方程
But, it turns out, when you put all these substitutions in,
但是 我们发现 当你讲所有这些都代入之后
it looks pretty scary.
方程看起来非常吓人
But, remember, it's not that bad.
但是 请记住 它并不那么糟糕
We're just plugging one value
我们只是将一个值
from one equation into another.
从一个方程带到另一个中
Solve this for t*, then substitute back
解出 t* 并代回
into the ray equations to get Ix, Iy, and Iz.
射线方程中以获得 I_x、I_y 和 I_z
Now, I know we've gone kind of fast,
我们知道我们走得有点快
but the next exercise will let you practice
但下一个练习题会让你多练练
computing intersection points for yourself. aimozhen.com/pixarinabox
计算焦点 aimozhen.com/pixarinabox